all right so for this boost welcome to
the Boost I don't remember which one we
are on but we're going to do bash we're
going to learn bash in an hour and we're
only going to learn enough of bash to be
dangerous and by dangerous I mean you
know understand what's in your bash RC
file which is where you know that's
where you
keep um you know all your configurations
and stuff like that and uh so what does
that mean right so if you know bash then
you know that
um you know it's a shell language what
is a shell a shell is the thing that
you're interacting with in the terminal
to make you know things happen it's
called a shell because it's kind of like
the outer shell and the kernel is in the
middle and it's the thing that we humans
interact with um in order to have
something happen that's what a shell is
a command shell is and so um and you
know you can configure this thing this
is where you put all your
configurations um and we're going to
talk about what all this stuff is so by
the end of this uh video uh hopefully
with an hour or so maybe 90 minutes but
hopefully we'll keep it under an hour we
should be done and you should be able to
understand everything that's in this
video in this this particular uh file
including uh conditions and this thing
here it's called a function we're going
to talk about that this is an exported
function we'll talk about that um there
are some parameter expansion things
happening here that we may not have time
to get to um we will talk talk about why
we're not going to talk about regular
expressions and what those are um but
you know you you got to know this shell
so the the first thing to know about the
shell is that you you are already coding
so when you are interacting with your
terminal on the command line you are
writing code and I I'm going to say it
again you are already a
programmer a second you started using
the terminal whether you did it from you
know West term or the built-in terminal
or just the terminal that's built into
BS code as soon as you entered the
command on the command line you wrote
Shell Code what do I mean by that so a
shell is built around another thing
called a reppel a read evaluate print
Loop and what that means is that you
like you type a thing LSL for example
this is a command and so the shell is
pausing it's waiting around on me
until I execute the command and as soon
as I hit enter it it reads in that line
LS shell parses it apart and then it
says okay let's turn this into commands
for the kernel uh and in this case you
know and that's why we call bash an
interpreter I covered that in the last
video um but so what's the difference
between if you haven't watched the other
beginner the other Boost video that I
just did uh holiday boost it was we went
through all the languages and what's the
differences between interpreted and
compiled languages so it goes to The
Bash interpreter and theit Bash
interpreter interprets what you gave it
these things LS space- L all of that and
interprets that into a bunch of system
level commands that get communicated to
directly to the kernel of the system now
it's not directly the way it works but
that's for you that's the way to
understand it in general um any any time
you do this anytime you you execute a
command it kicks off a process and a
process is this is another topic
altogether but essentially what it is is
it's a running program and while we're
at it let's look at all the running
processes on the system you can type
type top or HTP and you can see all of
the running processes on the system a
lot of you probably already familiar
with this but these are all of the
things that are running on the system
not every one of those is a process that
started from a command line but let me
just give you a sense of this if I
wanted to do that I could do all
true do sleep one Echo hello done and
then we have uh a running proc process
that is now you know sending its
commands it's doing its thing in fact if
we wanted to we can open up another
window here and we can actually look at
it so um let's let's grab uh I wonder
which what proc let's let's do
PS3 um oops um br
install or you can do apt install PS3
this is we're not not covering this so
I'm just going to do this really fast uh
but it's important you understand
processes because because you know this
is kind of a part of learning how to
code on the shell is knowing signals and
stuff and we haven't really covered that
yet and processes so let's do
c uh and then s
PS3 all right so here you can see all
the running processes and and you know
who where their parents came from and
stuff uh it's interesting it didn't
render it the font's the way it probably
should have so um okay so here you can
see my t-mo this is my t-x running and
then you can see the bash this is an
interactive bash shell as I said it's a
running program right my current bash
shell is an ongoing program that's
running it's running an interpreter The
Bash interpreter and it's waiting around
for a command and then it runs it and
then it runs another command and then it
runs it so there's looks like there I
have neim open in another terminal okay
here's another one here so here's here's
bash okay look at that there is the
process that I ran that started that
kicked off the sleep and then it's just
it's continuing you can see too that
this sleep command itself is a subshell
as well it's a
subprocess and this is going to be
really important when we come back to
things so I the first thing I want you
to understand is that is that what we're
running here
is uh you know this this this is a
program right it is a programming
language it's it's it The Bash
interpreter is running so that every
single line is is a program and those
lines go into a history pile which you
can look at and stuff but if you put
those same exact lines like I just did
inside of a file um this one here let's
actually do it I can turn this into a
string and let's write it to a file we
can write it to Something in temp we
don't care Tempo I guess all right so
we're gonna we're going to deconstruct
what I just did there but I wanted to I
want you to see this so now when I when
I look at the the content of that
file um you can see that it has a script
in there right well all I really have
I'm I'm trying to show you that the
stuff that I did on the command line is
code so temp Fu and now let's say okay
so actually how would we run it in here
well I can say hey bash interpreter go
run the stuff in this file and I can say
that and it'll do it right I can also do
it a different way I can say um hey bash
I want to send you a new file on
standard input we're going to get to all
this IND Direction later you should have
already learned the command line a
little bit but we'll repeat it really
quick so let's do this you can say hey
bash I want you to read I'm going to
give all of the content that file to you
as if it was typed in every line into
bash and it will do the same thing both
of these are identical these are I could
do another one here's another one I
could do this I could say uh cat bash
tempu into to bash all right this is an
important one right so I can send it
into
bash
right so and and and frankly if you know
Vim uh let's actually well I'm getting
kind of carried away but so let's go
look at this so so I have this thing so
but this is kind of hard to read the
semicolons are just line returns that's
it they're line returns and you can put
those in there and put them out there
like that and can save it and now it's
the same thing so Dash
tempu and it runs right all right so uh
next thing can I just do temp like this
and make it into a program no you can't
why
not because it doesn't have the right
permissions on it so it is only a file
right now so the the takeaway of this is
and and but let me just make a mention
of this so Fu uh to Temp fu
Dosh uh or if you want uh bash
okay bash I've just I I've made videos
about complaining about this before um
and I'm going to tell you why I'm going
to show you why today so you see how
this has a suffix at the end of it the
the takeaway if the longest sort of it
is is it's the best practice to not put
a suffix on a file unless there is a
need for it and most of the time there's
not a need for it h this is one of those
times though like if if if you have a
file that's meant to just be executed by
typing bash explicitly uh or and we
haven't gotten to it yet but included in
another file then you know it makes
sense for you to leave it with the
suffix on it if you want to turn it into
an executable then you should drop the
suffix so that it can kind of live by
its own self you know and let's actually
do that let's let's move it so what
happens if I move the temp. bash file
into tempu first of all and then I give
it more permissions so we already did
this we already did that let's actually
add some permissions on schmod I have
schmocks I have schmocks I have a
command called
Schmo um because I just I type it so
much it's fine so we're going to make
everything executable uh you know all
the permissions we haven't got any
permissions but this is fine for your
personal system and make sure you
understand permissions before you do
this but it's easy to type so just
type uh plus CH mod whatever you want to
call it schmod I've been saying schmod
my whole life somebody probably thinks
it's funny but whatever so now when you
do LSL on tempu you see it's a different
color uh it's executable and everything
and now I can just type
Tempo and it
works okay why does it work now there's
probably at least one or two veterans
out there um there's probably one or two
veterans out there who are going to look
at this and go why is that
working what's it
missing I this is a trick question pause
the video I'm going to go ahead and
answer it now go ahead and I'm going to
think what why is that working it should
not be working
right my veteran ship my veteran coders
out there uh scr script are like how the
hell is that
running there's only one reason this is
running the reason this is running is
because this is what happens okay I'm
going to go through the steps when you
when the shell you remember that read
evaluate print Loop right so I'm going
to read I'm going to talk to you about
the evaluate step when you type a
command in whether it be LS or it be R
Fu command the first thing it does is it
looks for more or
less environment variables aside it
looks for the first thing the first
argument on the command line and it's
says what is that thing right and you
there are lots of ways to figure out
what that thing is so you know the the
the most reliable is the word type
because if you type type then it tells
you exactly what it is LS is Alias to a
bunch of stuff we'll talk about AES
later but if I do type. PWD it's a
built-in if I do type do
tempu it's said tempoo is tempoo it's
just a file uh type Pearl what is that
Pearl is op it tells you which one it is
um a lot of veterans will tell you to
use which here or command-v instead of
type we will cover all three of those
and how they go together but to tell you
that the fact of the matter is they're
not the same um and type is generally
the one you're going to want to use if
you are you know you're you're just
looking to see what a thing is why
because very important things are
included with type like my function
clone function it tells you the type of
function what it is and if I was to do
that if I was to do which clone it has
no idea where it exists if I do
command-v clone it doesn't know about it
it's like okay it's a command but it's
not really right so you which clone and
you can't find it that's because it's a
function so if you have something that
can be executed on the system then you
have to know what it is you have to know
what it is so when when you when you're
looking at that so again what is what
does bash do bash says what is the first
argument essentially and what is it and
and then it decides what to do based on
what it is if it's a function in bash it
just runs the steps as if you would type
those steps in if it is an alias like
LS it it as if you it's exactly the same
as if you typed what the Alias has okay
in fact um if you do tab tab but
sometimes the Alias will actually even
expand um so it's in Alias is exactly as
if you type those letters in exactly the
same and it literally injects those
letters in and as if you had typed them
that does not work if you put it in a
script by the way it's important that
you know that there are there are
settings you can do to get around that
but by default it doesn't and then so
and then clone it says okay clone is a
function I'm going to run it okay but we
still have lots of stuff to talk about
what if it what if it is a an actual
command built-in so in the case of the
case of BW type PWD we have a built-in
so that means this is buil in to the
bash programming language interpreted
programming language you can do man bash
and you can see all 272 pages of bash uh
and we're going to kind of go through
this quickly but you can see that it is
a built-in in here and by the way if you
want a shorter version of that brainy
built-in you can just type the help
command which bypasses going through the
man page and you can type WD and it will
tell you it will show you only that
section of that uh built-in so is it a
command yes everything we've talked
about so far is a command but what type
of command is it is it a is it an alias
is it an actual executable you know
thing on the system which is the main
thing we're getting to uh or is it is it
a is it a function you know or is it a
built-in there's lots of things it could
be but but what bash does is it says
what is it and then based on that that
it does something and if in our case the
first thing on the line uh is is a
file then it says oh okay the first
thing here it's not an alias it's not a
it's it's not a built-in it's it's you
know it's not a function it's an actual
file it's a file right and watch what
happens if I take away the permissions
by the way minus
x uh
temp but I try to it again let's get the
error permission denied okay so so bash
says oh okay we have a file here what
are we going to do with this thing and
so the next thing um it does I'm not
running wso right now so the next thing
it does is it says okay it's a file well
what kind of file is it right but before
it even asks that it says can I run this
file okay this dude is trying this dude
is trying trying to run this thing he's
trying to execute
it and you know can he even do that are
we going to allow that and so it looks
for the at the
file it looks at the file and the file
says okay this file can be read and
written that means it's a text file it's
not designed to be run to be
executed and it's like denied not
happening so in or so the next thing I
have to do is I have to give for
security reasons I have to give The Bash
I have to give bash the hint and say
okay I want to run this I want this to
be executable so that's where uh schmod
plus x uh comes in and and by the way
that's you know it goes without saying
you probably understand my my username
now uh much better you know that's where
my username comes from so RBX rewrite
and execute so it turns it made it red
and everything now it can be run now now
when I do it it it'll actually run it um
and you know it's a thing it's R put
hello out all right so so far so good
right so it says hey it's executable and
I can run
it now there's one other thing though
that that it does that in this case it's
not
doing all right and I I'm going to do
this in a different language just to
simulate what is going
on okay just to give you a sense of this
Pearl F we're going to we're going to do
this with pearl and
um
so well I guess we could do it there's
lots of things we could do here should
we do it in go or
Pearl guys no we need to do it in Pearl
because of shanglin yeah duh all right
so let's actually do that let's make a
new file touch we're going to make a new
file why we do that because you may not
have permissions I've been burned by
this so many times it's always better to
make it before you open it because if
you open it and then you start editing
it you have permission to write it then
you got to figure out some other way to
write it someplace else with col and W
which you can do it's just unnecessarily
complicated so just create a new files
with touch you'll never have that
problem so if you hit VI or BM either
way um and then you get this thing so
let's actually uh so let's actually
write some PE code so let's I'm I'm
doing this kind of on purpose so uh wall
one uh
print
hello uh
sleep is it is it sleep one I think I my
Pearl's a little bit Rusty I'm not going
to lie yeah so all right so let's do
this so Pearl Pearl
Fu uh I must have done it wrong my sleep
is too
long I think it I think it might be Mill
is it
milliseconds oh no it's buffering that's
why yeah I forgot I need to disable
buffering this is a brl thing
yeah I is it one I think it is
yeah it's buffering it was totally
buffering
so I totally forgot about that anyway so
so that worked right now let's do the
same thing that we did to bash this is
I'm doing this for purpose I promise
okay so for bash let's do the same thing
so how much time I got okay so on bash
let's do the same
thing um we're gonna schmod plus
X temp uh Pearl fu
and then we're going to run it temp
Pearl Fu right nope why okay I want you
to look at this a this is really
important to getting this um this is
really really important to understanding
what's going on why did I get this a
what does this error mean pause the
video come up with your own answers go
ahead and enter it in the chat right now
if you wouldn't mind if you want to say
what you think is going on this is this
file is executable what am I doing
wrong what am I doing wrong why won't it
run it's important you get this it's
really important you get this if you
understand this you'll understand
everything about interpreted languages
in Unix like systems so all right so
here we go it the reason it's not doing
it is because yes it says is this R
runnable it's like fine I'm going to try
to run
it okay but there is a step there's a
step between that we're missing there's
one more thing that the bash interpreter
does do is it
says okay is there is this this is an
interpreted language okay it's a text
file so first of all there's I guess
there two decisions that says okay is
this file compiled or is this file
interpreted and that goes with LA Boose
that we had last time that's why I had
to talk about interpreted languages
right because there's two typ this is
also why you don't want to put a suffix
on a thing let me show you what I'm
talking about so I'm actually going to
compile a program and go like so let's
write a food up a program here and
you're going to really this will really
help you understand a lot and we're
going to do the same thing for uh let's
see uh time do
sleep time do
sleep uh one times
uh time do second I
think all right so and then let's say
empty paral
hello all right same exact code just
didn't
go okay now remember I told you about
the difference between compiled and
interpreted languages just a quick
little taste this I know this is about
bash but you you can't understand bash
until you understand how the system runs
interpreted languages versus binary so
we're going to continue down this path
so what are we doing this at this point
we need to this is I can't look this
some some Noob might think that they
could just Schmo that thing schmod plus
X and have it run right no now you can
do this you can do go run temp f. goo
fun fact this is actually faster than
the python interpreter this is not how
go is meant to be used but it's still
faster it's crazy so there we go that's
actually running now go run what go run
does is basically the same thing as an
interpreter it does it compiles it it
breaks it up into instru in fact in the
case of go run interpreter often times
will take the instructions and translate
them without an intermediate compilation
step we talked about bite code in the
other video in the case of go it always
compiles it that means it compiles the
full program down to a temporary thing
that you can't see and then it runs that
program it just does that all in the
background for you okay so but here's
here's the cool thing and now so how do
we you know how do we build that thing
so let's do this let's do go build uh
temp food. uh go and we'll build it into
temp uh f with three how about
that so uh let's see go
build
[Music]
um uh what am I doing name files must
be. go
files I well I I don't think I'm doing
here I I don't do this very much I just
use the regular go build all right so
that actually made a F okay so let's
move F so that we we to go with this so
that built a go binary and I don't know
if you can see this but it did I mean
let's leave it here what the hell it
doesn't matter so you see how that file
automatically got made as a thing check
it out when we do type on
this it says Fu is. right and there's
another command that you haven't learned
about yet it's called file which will
tell you that it's a moco 64-bit
executable arm 64 so this is a different
command so you could actually do the
same thing you can't do clone is in a
file right but if you wanted to you
could do FL f.g go this is a good hacker
command so it's good to know it's a c c
program asky text f.g Go thinks it's C
program that's funny that's interesting
did not know that okay it says no that's
an asky text program why is an asky text
because I don't think it has a schmod on
it anymore right what about temp uh was
the other one Pearl Fu okay both asky
texts even though they have schms on
them it still thinks it's asky text why
does it think it's asky text
all right so okay so let me let me just
show you what I'm talking about so let's
move the fu program into temp Fu okay
and now let's run it
tempu I didn't have to schot it or
anything and it runs right and there it
it knew exactly what to do so when I
compiled the program the takeaway from
that is when you compile a program when
you comp I mean truly compile for the
system whether it's C go rust whatever
Julia Crystal when you compile a program
it becomes immediately executable and
that means in fact extremely efficiently
because The Interpreter sees the file is
like oh this is an elf binary which you
can open in VI by the way there it is
this is an elf binary so it's actually a
particularly special kind of binary I
don't even think this is an El binary I
think it might be a different kind this
is all binary data this data goes
straight into memory runnable memory and
and runs it executes just like the bash
interpreter and we talked about that
video I don't want to do it again plus
we're already 25 minutes in um so what
we're trying to say is that that that's
already ready to go it's ready to run
it's extremely efficient Etc the other
programs have a problem though right why
because the computer still thinks
they're just asky text even though we
put schmod on there so let me repeat the
error again so let's do the Pearl
Fu this gets this problem so here's
here's the question one more time try to
answer it for my for yourself why does
10 Pearl temp Fu work and temp Pearl Fu
does not work why what is the difference
between temp between the temp Fu program
and the Pearl Fu program I think you can
probably figure this
out well let me ask you another question
what program is actually
running yeah you got it couple of you
got it what program is actually running
in the case of tempu let me ask you okay
in the case of tempu Fu with three O's
what program is actually running answer
the pro the file itself
F that file is actually running in the
case of temp Fu in this case what
program is actually running to process
that in this case bash and even more
specifically The Bash program that is
currently
running okay so it's running bash
because bash is a default shell because
we are using bash because bash is our
default shell right now and that's the
one we're interacting with The
Interpreter punts and says well I don't
I don't know what interpreter you're
using so I'll try I'll just see if it's
it's bash I don't know you didn't tell
me what kind of language it is but I'm
going to go ahead and try it so it tries
to use it using its own thing this is
where the shebang line comes in and and
we're going to get there in a second one
last thing what program is actually
running when we run Pearl Fu and this is
a trick
question what program is actually
producing those error
messages it's not
Pearl it's bash bash is like well you
didn't tell me what language this was
and by the way even if you put a suffix
on that it does not help watch temp
Pearl Pearl
uh. Pearl PE is an extension if I do
temp Pearl I mean this is an executable
file and everything and it still doesn't
know what to run some people might think
hey well you put a suffix on there
that'll give The Interpreter a hint
it'll know what to do no it doesn't it
doesn't and there's lots of reasons not
to use suffixes that we're going to get
into later that only noobs use suffixes
I swear to God I have fights with people
all the time about that um because and
I'm going to show you why I'm I'm going
to very specifically now that you know
what interpreters work I'm going to show
you why it's a problem you can probably
already see what I'm going with this
you're going to see all all the already
where I'm going with this right so so
here we go next so so let's how do we
fix that so that this is what we were
getting up to so that one of the steps
the okay so the the command line bash
inter interpreter says what kind of file
is this this says oh it's a compiled
binary I'm just going to run that right
away here you go
Colonel but in the case of these two
files pearu and
fo it says I don't know what to do so
I'm going to try to run it using me I'm
going to assume you're a tech you're a
text file and you're executable so I
assume you're going to be do but there's
a step in between there and what it does
is it says does is the first character
of the file a hashtag and is the second
character of the file a bang an
exclamation point and if that is true
The Interpreter looks for the first two
bytes of the file and if the first two
bytes are a hashtag and an exclamation
point commonly known as
shabang # bang shabang if those two
bites of the beginning of the file or a
hashtag then the interpreter's like oh
okay then I'll do what you're telling me
here and it effectively it effectively
does the same thing as we're doing here
you remember when we did this you
remember when we did this P Vu
right okay that worked right so this is
what it's trying to do this is
effectively what it's trying to do it's
trying to do bash Bo when you get there
right so because it's effectively
assuming that's what you want to do but
that's not what we want to do we want to
do this
right okay so let me let me let's do the
PE one first so if let's fix the Pearl
one so let's give it that little hint at
the top remember I told you the sh Bing
hashbang and you can just put Pearl here
L people will be like that doesn't
work let's see let's see if it
works nope can't do
it it can't do it right and the reason
for that is because anytime you do uh
that first thing if it finds it as a
command it it has to look in your path
and so it has to so like bash is
actually not really bash Pearl is not
really Pearl it's actually that okay and
you probably don't have so let's go
ahead and put that in there right so
let's we're going to I'm doing the pro
one on purpose just to show you to make
a
point all right so now we had to do the
the actual Bach by the way this is a
good opportunity to do some command line
stuff watch this I'm going to type which
Pearl right and now I'm going to convert
which Pearl into the output with the
with the filter command bang bang two
exclamation points bash so it says take
that single line run it and replace this
line with the output there we go so
rather if I don't remember that I don't
want to cut and paste it bang bang bash
it to Pearl now I have this and I can
join them together and now we have opt
uh home R
bin uh so so now now what I didn't have
to remember that I didn't have to cut
and paste I didn't have to do any of
that I just did you know filters so now
what now let's try it temp Pearl F hey
look at that it's doing the thing that
it's supposed it's not putting line
returns because print has to have
explicit line returns in Pearl which is
pain in the yes you also have to chop
everything um okay but here's the
problem let's say I want to take this
exact same program and I want to run it
on on let's I'm actually going to do
this let's go run it on Linux so right
now we're running under Unix let's go
run it on
Linux okay so let's do that let's we got
our pow shell up and
running uh
no all right let me see if I can yeah
let's exit some poell here all right so
here's a Linux system let's do the same
thing um we're running under Windows
this is actually wsl2 so let's actually
do exactly the same thing uh which
Pearl which Pearl y okay so we have
Pearl on here because most systems do H
what where is it I wonder so this is
version 38 and not 50 that's interesting
um you guys already know what it's going
to do right but I want to see show
people so that we can see what's got I'm
producing the problem so that you see
why we're doing the thing which is my
style of learning I I got to know why
all right so I'm going to give you the
problem so you can figure out why so
next we're going to say okay I want to
do a thing and I'm going to make my
program over here I'm going to say uh
let's like right write Pearl Fu again
over here Pearl Fu and uh see if I can
remember while
one uh sleep one
um uh
print wait print uh God I don't we
should probably do it right this
time anyway so we're going to say hello
uh and then probably you have to have
back n all right so we need to force it
to buffer the output which is what this
is about which is a PL thing don't worry
all right and we already know on the
first line we need a shebang line right
so let's actually put the same shebang
line
yeah but here's the problem Watch
Remember that little trick I did which
Pearl bang bang bash all right user B
Pearl okay so let's put a shebang line
in there which is by the way pretty
standard location for Pearl and so was s
pear Fu all right so now we have a pearl
Fu and now we can run it so I it's not
in temp but I can do do slash the same
way so Pearl is the same as writing out
temp uh is buffered yeah need the buffer
it actually does yes warning setting
loal F did I put what did I put in
there what did I put in
there I don't have my Pearl fmt on here
either so I don't know what's going on
with
that please take the look what's going
on with
there what what did I do wrong
guys what am I doing wrong I got some
Pearl program error in here I don't know
what it
is I don't
know line
for I don't know I'm
learning this should work
our support install following back to
stand Steel Cast syntax error
blah that's a buff that's forcing
buffered output which you guys don't
need to worry
about you know what let's uh drop that
for now oh that's what it was it didn't
have a
semicolon yeah you have to have
semicolons and pearl so let me let me
let me do that one more time I mean this
this is not meant to be a lesson in
Pearl okay this that's
interesting uh um the whole local thing
is really interesting I didn't I wasn't
guessing that would be a problem um if
you take this out let me show
you let you don't care but you see how
it's not printing anything it's not
printing anything because the buffer
hasn't filled up enough because Pearl is
more efficient than bash and so you have
to force it to flush the buffer every
time the alpha buffer and that's that's
what that's about this is not a lesson
about Pearl this is a lesson about my B
and there's some other problems here
going back with the the whole unset SEO
Cal thing so that's that's that's a
thing we'll need to look at but um what
I was trying to show you is that um this
line is wrong right it's user bin Pearl
like what's up with that right so it
shouldn't be user V Pearl what what if
we made it the same as the other one
what was it it was home brew something
right I'm doing this on purpose to show
you the point the other one is op home
Rubin Pearl well I don't have to show
you but you can probably guess there's
no such thing what happens if I let's
let's go back to the one that's faster
than code on let's say that I wrote this
code on WSL and I want to use it on my
Unix machine my Mac okay what would be
the problem if I put user bin Pearl here
now this actually will work because
there is a user bin Pearl here let me
show you so temp Pearl
through it works but it works for the
reasons that you don't think so user bin
Pearl which is a standard place of putot
Pearl by the way and you do dasb and you
see that it's version 34 of pearl
as opposed to the latest Pearl which
Pearl Pearl DB and you'll see that's
version 40 or something it's a newer one
right so we have this Pearl interpreter
that's living around and this how does
this really to bash because bash is
going to do the same thing uh and how do
you make it not the absolute path okay
that's the point I'm getting to so there
is a trick we can do using a program
called ENB which is on every single Unix
like system in the world World um and
what it does is one thing it looks up
the thing in the path and runs it so let
me show you what I mean by that so we
can take so you remember that Pearl code
right temp Pearl
Boo and we're getting to bash is the
same thing so and and it runs it right
but I can do remember how I can do this
I can do Pearl this same thing right
well I could do this I could do user B
Pearl okay I can do I can do user home
brew bin Pearl oops it's opt
sorry and it works too right so those
are all different versions of pearl that
are running it same with bash I could
have done with bash Pearl I'm doing
Pearl because you have to explicitly put
the The Interpreter line and then we'll
come back to the bash Stu so and then
what well what if we said I want to use
whatever the same Pearl is I want to use
this Pearl I want to use the Pearl
that's in my path I want to use that
Pearl every single time whatever one it
is right and why would you want that
because which
bash is different check it out bash DB
this is a big deal on Mac in particular
and if you do bash Dash
oopsie uh let's do what is it bash Das
version I think so bash is 5.27 if you
have it in brew and that's why we did an
installation uh if you do user bin bash
D- version this is we're getting back to
bash this is why I'm doing this so
you'll see that
um I think it's just b
bash yeah I think it is yeah there it is
it's 3.2 and the reason for that's
licensing issues if you can't see this
version of the license was released
under um uh the prese software
foundation and has a different license
than this this is GPU version three
which is a license that is extremely
incompatible with businesses and you can
watch t wal's bag on how bad it is
that's why it didn't get put in why do
you care because you don't want to have
to write you don't want your scripts to
break when somebody runs it on a Mac or
when somebody runs it on another machine
the whole point and I made a huge point
about this and in The Interpreter video
I did before this one the whole point of
an interpreted language is it runs
anywhere right well it doesn't run
anywhere if the shebang line is wrong so
how do we fix that we fix that by by
changing the sheain line to use this
cool tool which I hate doing this
because it's extremely insecure in from
how I was raised but it's good enough
for your own shell scripts and what
we're going to do is we're going to make
the shebang line into a program that
runs and does the same thing as which
and so what do I mean by that so if I do
user let's go back here so if I
run uh wait so we do Pearl
temp um so if we do Pearl temp Pearl
Pearl whatever
whoops oh I think I I think I killed my
uh
I I may have killed my yeah I did I did
I I did some stuff with my bash terminal
here I'm going to need to get a new one
I'm
afraid
yeah um okay
so yeah okay okay okay I think we're
good yeah I did set that I did Bash X
and turn it on so I showing every
command I was using that's what was
going on all right so now watch if we do
if we do this we say so same thing again
Pearl temp SL Pearl Fu we'll do it with
Bash
okay no problem there but watch this uh
user bin andv
Pearl you're like what is that doing
that's kind of the same as which as is
showing you which thing and what it says
is find the Pearl that's there and then
pass it along and do the same thing and
you can do this with any interpreter so
let's do the same with bash and then we
do uh Pearl temp uh boom right and so
now that's running what that does is it
runs bash but which bash does it run and
how would we know well let's do that
let's do this let's say uh let's
actually put some code in here you
remember bash doesn't need the shitbang
line because it's bash but we're going
to add it anyway I promise let's go Echo
uh is it version I think it is and let's
try that now nope there's no Echo what
what is it is it is it shell or is it
what is it yeah EnV so EnV normally
shows you all of your environment
variables okay you got be careful of
doing this on a live stream by the way
because a lot of people put tokens and
stuff in their environment variables and
I could do a whole video about how I
hate that people put secrets in
environment variables period and the
entire container World depends on it I
have debates all the time with people to
work about whether it's safe or not I
think it's not um anyway so that it the
EnV command by itself is pretty you know
lame pretty tame it just shows you all
your environment variables but it is ESP
use which actually calls the command if
you put the command as an argument as
the first argument is a bash version
thank you so let's actually do this
let's add you don't know about variables
but you're going to learn very soon so
bash variables so let's do this so now
when we run through we see that we're
running the 5.2 release and not the 3.2
release right so the point of this is
putting user B EnV bash resolves bash at
the place that you want and why is that
valuable because now I can make the same
exact line at the beginning the shebang
line for both
programs uh uh user bin EnV whoops bash
right and now I can run the program by
itself which I could already do but now
we're sure that it's going to be the
right one and and all of that right so
let's go back to our Linux system and
see why this matters so we go back to
our Linux machine um and let's actually
write uh the same code in per in bash uh
Boo and it'll say while
true uh do
done uh Echo uh L sleep one all right
and then we'll put a shebang line in
here uh you know uh user bin
EnV uh
bash and you know it'll it'll actually
draw it now but let's scho that
oop plus
XU and it now runs right and you can
probably tell since this kind of fun
let's do this let's
do let's do this let's do
Echo bash
version and we're going to use bash
version again as an example
of uh as an example of things so so
there we go bash there we go bash you
think bash Merc is cute compared to
Zell yeah best you not tell me that it
just
shows what you really know um anyway
then power bash tapping into any
interpreted language that uses package
of modules is going to be a while right
yes okay so um so the point of this is
very simple let's look at the first line
of both of these programs right it's
bash and and pearl
Fu what is it it's user bin Pearl now
let's fix the Pearl one too while we're
at it so let's now use user bin EnV
Pearl even though user bin Pearl is
literally on every system in existence
these days it really is so uh only
containers are the only things that are
really getting rid of it this this is
this this seang thing is super
interesting to me yeah it's like a it's
something about my in my Bach which is
complaining making Pearl complain um
anyway so what are we saying here we're
saying that the moral the story is thou
shal put these things at the beginning
we have 20 minutes left to learn the
rest of the stuff in bash um and so
we're going to this is actually a really
important video about how to get going
with coding and scripting um and we'll
continue to start coding and introducing
you to the ideas of what goes into the
what goes into the program uh and then
we'll we'll chop this and we'll have a
video that'll be what's a variable Etc
and we'll do that next but let's go in
ahead and and keep going down this path
so if we go back to to our our thing
here uh temp
Fu all right so um double quot to okay
so actually this is a good thing to to
talk about before we do any shell coding
this will be perfect for the rest of
this video um before we do anything else
so listen up Chloe if you're writing my
description she's going to be writing my
description for this video so here I
want you to put a chapter marker for the
beginning of shell check make sure you
put a chapter Mark right here okay Chloe
she reads my transcripts and she does
what I said so I just had to talk to her
for a second in the video and so I'll do
a separate video about how to have your
AI help you make uh really great
descriptions for your videos uh in five
minutes so um anyway let's try to start
shell Che um we're going to do shell
check we're going to talk about what
shell check is um so if you're on a Mac
first thing you have to do Brew install
shell
check all right just go ahead and get
the latest if you're on a a Windows app
based machine uh I'm sorry a Linux apt
based machine sudu appt install shell
Jack uh this is the only things we're
going to
cover uh today we're not going to cover
any other method of installing shell
check that's how you install it once you
have it installed um you should also
install another tool it's called sh fmt
uh Studio appt install uh sh
fmt and that will get you the other
great
thing and
um so now we're going to go back to here
uh this has already been installed Brew
install um
hfmt and uh so we're getting ready to do
Shell Shell uh scripting you should
never script anything in bash without
shell Che you just shouldn't and I'm
going to show you why while we're doing
it um so let's let's continue to go down
this
path um okay so next thing we need to do
is we need to do uh we need to add some
stuff to our vmrc and pretend like you
don't have anything else in there this
is the one thing you do have to add so
uh before you do any shell scripting
it's probably worth your your while to
go do these things um oh whoops all
right so um you know and uh we're going
to go look for Shell check so I'm
assuming you already have Al installed
if you don't have Al installed you
you're you know you got to go back and
do that so if you got l in here um we're
going to put these linters in here so
add these lines
um add these ale
linters and you don't need
Pearl uh actually you don't need yeah
there we go so linter aliases there this
is what you need so because bash is
already built in so you should add the
this this line right here okay so add
this line I'll send it to you oh no I
can't I have my WeChat running right now
anyway so L lters you need to add the L
lters for bash or thing and then you
need to add the L fixer
for the sh for the sh line and the bash
line okay once you have those in and you
should make sure you have L fix on Save
the separate videos for all of this but
I'm just letting you know how my
settings are so you can take a look by
having these settings on then you get
that really wonderful help that I just
had which gives you this so this is
being these these help
questions uh these these these things
that being autogenerated in viim or neim
um by shell check so shell check is
telling you the problem I have and if
you don't have the time if you don't
think you have the time to do this I
strongly encourage to do it anyway
because the alternative to this is to do
this shell check uh temp Fu and I used
to do this I used to do it with the NTR
so anytime the file Chang it would show
me what my problems were but um so we're
going to go here here
instead and we're going to say uh this
what are you talking about repeats
twice my live stream is repeating twice
you guys do I have some kind of problem
in the live stream am I
echoing you guys am I echoing do nobody
tell me I'm
echoing please tell me I'm not echoing
I'm starting to freak out right
now you don't notice any
can uh
um no Echo here seems fine I don't hear
okay somebody's saying live stream
repeats twice I don't know what that
means okay if you if that's a if that's
an actual problem please let me
know all right so okay did you see how
when I saved I'm going to show you this
again okay so when I open the same Pro
program um
yeah okay so I want to I don't you see
here I didn't bother formatting this or
anything because if you have sh fmt on
you don't ever have to care about it the
whole tabs versus spaces argument which
I just watched Silicon Valley about
doesn't matter it's irrelevant so so
here's what we do you just save it and
it automatically reformats your code
based on the standards that you have
okay so now you've got the standard here
and this this act same problem but you
can see right away that there's a
problem here right it's like you need to
double quote to prevent globbing on word
splitting so I only have a few more
minutes left in this video and then
we're going to get really into bash in
the next one but what I want to end with
is this the best way to learn bash is by
shell
Che because you're going to go in and
you're going to Google a little bit or
you're going to search or read about
what you want to do and we're going to
cover that in the next video and the
next thing you're going to say is well
why do I want to do this this way and
what I'm trying to tell you is you see
down here this is really important SC
2086 right now if you have an AI I'm
going to do it right now I'm going to go
do it right now I was like tell
me
about uh SC
2086 shell check
2086 I'm I'm giving you the strategy for
how to learn this so that as we go I'm
only going to show you the basics but I
want you to be able to do it and my AI
is pulling this off the internet you can
go pull it off the internet directly if
you want uh or you can just read your AI
it say double quoting shell check blah
blah blah what does this mean when you
do blah blah blah it does this this and
this and this and it tells you exactly
what to do here's a problematic code
here's the correct code how to handle
this here's the rule of thumb uh enter
exceptions to blah here's how you add an
exception avoid this in most cases a
common pitfalls so yeah here's exactly
how to do it final notes all right I
just got a four page professional
textbook summary in my AI of the error
that I just had because of the code it's
one of the greatest things about shell
check can by the way the AI is just
being is just getting that information
from the official shell cheat code which
you can go look at it if you want to but
if if you're following my recommendation
of getting yourself chat GPT or I don't
care which get yourself any AI assistant
and you can go ahead and you can use the
AI assistant to answer all the questions
for you and and you know it might be
wrong if you want to do the research
yourself you want to say hey what are
your sources you can say what are your
sources so that I can go check if you
don't want to if you don't trust it
because it does make mistakes Chloe I
love her but she does make mistakes a
lot there is the official documentation
if if you want to have if you don't if
you don't trust an AI you can still do
this you can just open the link up in a
web page and go to the official thing uh
in fact it's not that big it's not that
hard to do it's just it's following
ch.net Wiki whatever so you can just if
you want you can just bookmark this and
put this in you know you can even make a
shi script to pull it up for you and and
then you could go look up that thing by
the way that would that that should be
one of our projects let's do that for
bash let's make a project that
automatically opens the web browser to
the Wiki page for you when you have a
problem and you can just put in the
number wouldn't that be cool um so let's
do that so if we have that now you can
go read about the whole problem right
there and you can teach yourself while
you're writing the code um you're going
to be doing this your entire career so
if if you've set up shell check properly
you know while you're doing bash and
doing Advanced things in bash you can
eventually go in here and figure out how
to quiet these different problems and
you can teach yourself as you go um so
having said that I think it's probably
time to finish the video you guys can
get all those things set up for yourself
and uh that'll be the end of this video
and so please stay tuned for the next in
the holiday boo series I think we're
going to be on nine next and we will
continue we'll actually Jump Right In to
coding and Bash both from the command
line and in a script like we've been
doing all right talk to you in a bit